Well, all right. Let's talk about the
causes and effects of the
SpanishAmerican War. And baby, it is
American Empire test. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay. Now, in the last
video, I flapped my mouth hole
prodigiously about the debates that
arose between the imperialists and
anti-imperialists concerning America's
role on the international stage. In
other words, they argued over whether
the United States should or should not
pursue an overseas empire like all the
big-time European empires. And here's
where I tell you that they weren't just
sitting around on their brains and
having this debate for funsies. So, the
whole reason this argument flared up was
because in 1898, the United States was
on the brink of entering a war with
Spain. And spoiler alert, that war
actually happened and it became known as
the SpanishAmerican War. And there are
three main causes for it that you're
going to need to remember. Oh, and by
the way, if you want note, guys, to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Okay, so the first cause of
the war was the US desire to control the
Caribbean island nation of Cuba. Now,
why says you did the policymakers want
to control Cuba? Well, says I, there
were a lot of reasons, but the biggest
ones are as follows. First of all, you
remember the Monroe Doctrine which
proclaimed that the Western Hemisphere
belonged to the US and that European
intervention was unwelcome. Well, that
whole lifting the leg and claiming
what's ours mentality was still very
much enforced near the turn of the
century and Americans no likey Spain in
our house. And remember what I said in
the last video, namely that the US was
real keen to establish more of a
presence in the Caribbean after Alfred
the Mahan convinced everyone that naval
strength was the best way to project
power on the world states. Second,
remember that during industrialization,
American businesses invested heavily in
Cuba to create large operations for
exporting fruit and sugar, which is why
they were known as banana republics. And
then third, in 1895, Cuban nationalists
reignited a war of independence against
their Spanish colonizers. And despite
being vastly outnumbered by Spanish
forces, the Cubans successfully waged a
protracted war of attrition, relying on
guerilla tactics. Not to mention that
local diseases hit Spanish soldiers real
hard and drastically reduced their
numbers. And when it looked like the
Cubans were at the very threshold of
victory, President William McKinley
began making plans for US intervention
in Cuba against Spain. And to be fair,
McKinley did do his best to negotiate a
peaceful end to the Cuban conflict so
that normal trade could resume. But once
the warship Maine blew up, there wasn't
much hope for further negotiation. And
I'll tell you more about that in a
moment. And then the second cause of the
war was the widespread influence of
yellow journalism. You see, although
much of the public opposed a war with
Spain, a group of influential
journalists got busy changing that
opinion. And so New York editors like
Joseph Pulitzer and William Randph Hurst
competed with each other for newspaper
sales. And they did so by publishing
sensational and often exaggerated
accounts of Spanish atrocities against
the Cubans. And that's not much
different than what we experience today.
Like everybody knows that exaggerated
and rage batty content on social media
is exactly what gets the clicks and is
handsomely rewarded by the dark lord of
the algorithm. And so these yellow
journalists were basically doing the
same thing. and their efforts very much
worked to change public opinion on the
war, mainly in New York, and arouse a
fervent jingoism among their readers.
Now, jingoism, when being defined,
describes an extreme nationalism that
calls for an aggressive foreign policy
in order to project power on the world
stage. And that jingoism meant that
fighting Spain over Cuba became kind of
a necessity if Americans were going to
show the world who was boss. And
finally, the third major cause of the
war was the explosion of the American
warship, the USS M. See, even though war
had not yet been declared, President
McKinley had already sent a US warship
to Cuba. Hey, look, that is patently not
the move of a man trying to prevent war,
but the move of a man searching for even
the tiniest speck of justification to
start one. And as it turned out, in
February of 1898, the main exploded in
Havana Harbor, killing 266 US sailors.
Now, like 5 minutes after it exploded
and before any kind of investigation was
initiated to understand the causes of
the disaster, yellow journalists jumped
on it like a hungry man on a Christmas
ham and they went ahead and fully blamed
Spain for the explosion and the deaths
of the American sailors. And that
brought the jingoistic fervor of
Americans to a boil. And to many, it
seemed like a war against Spain was the
only way to preserve American honor on
the world stage. And therefore, in April
of 1898, McKinley asked Congress for a
declaration of war. And he got it. Now,
within that formal declaration of war,
Congress included something called the
Teller Amendment, which said that
postwar Cuba would be free and
independent, and that the US would only
be involved until Cuba was in a peaceful
and pacified state. And maybe that
sounds like a real win for the Cubans,
but I'll give you one guess to figure
out what has two thumbs and had the
right to decide whether Cuba was
pacified or not. It's this guy. So, the
language of the Teller Amendment allowed
for plenty of room for US involvement in
Cuba after the war. Now, ultimately, the
US won the war in only a few months, and
it was such a quick victory that it
became known as the splendid little war.
However, that makes it sound like the US
forces were altogether competent and
trained and effective, which they were
not. In fact, the US victory was so
quick because Spain was stretched thin
defending other territories in its
empire. And more to the point, the
Cubans themselves had brought the
conflict right to the edge of victory
and the US was able to swoop in and
finish it up. Okay, so the
SpanishAmerican War was splendid and
little, but the effects of this war were
massive because it formerly marked the
beginning of an overseas American
empire. And I'm in the mood to organize
these effects into three categories for
you. First, the peace treaty that ended
the war officially made the United
States the proud owner of an overseas
empire as they took over several Spanish
territories in the Caribbean and in the
Pacific. In the Caribbean, the US gained
control of Puerto Rico and not
surprisingly, Cuba. I mean, I don't
think it's going to be a shock to any of
you to find out that after the war
ended, US officials deemed Cuba unfit
for immediate self-ruule and therefore
require continued military occupation by
US forces. And that's a real bummer for
the Cubans. But don't worry because the
military occupation only lasted until
1902 when Cubans finally drafted their
own constitution and would be hereafter
an independent and free nation.
[laughter] Yeah, right. Wouldn't that be
hilarious if that's how it went? Now, as
the Cubans were drafting their
constitution, the US pressured them to
add and ratify something called the
Platt Amendment, which eliminated Cuban
sovereignty while affording the US a
significant amount of control on the
island. For example, the Plat Amendment
dictated that the Cuban government could
not sign treaties with other nations
without first getting permission from
the US. It also mandated that the US
could intervene if Cuban independence or
its economy was threatened. And again,
it was the US which would determine
whether a threat was worth intervention.
And in that way, even after Cuban
independence, Cuba was not fully
independent. Okay. Then the second
effect of the war was a significant
increase in America's involvement in
Asia. So the peace treaty also seated
the Pacific island of Guam to the United
States. And this Sweet Bippy proved a
real valuable strategic location for
accessing the US's most significant
territorial prize in the Pacific, namely
the Philippines. Now, I'll get back to
the Philippines when I talk about the
third effect, but for now, you just need
to realize that these Pacific
territories provided the US with much
greater access to Asian markets than
they ever had. And with the annexation
of Hawaii right at the end of the war,
look at this nice little territorial
path that the US had made for themselves
in order to get to those juicy Asian
markets. And of special importance was
the vast markets available in China.
Now, as I mentioned in the previous
video, for China, the 19th century was
uh rough. It was so rough, in fact, that
it became known by the cheery moniker,
the century of humiliation. Long story
short, on account of the superior
industrial strength of European nations,
China was essentially taken over, not
politically, but economically and carved
up into European spheres of influence.
And as a result, President McKinley
Secretary of State John Haye saw
America's economic opportunities in
China vanishing quicker than a fart in a
wind tunnel and decided to act. Hey sent
what was known as the open door note to
the European powers in China asking them
to observe an open door of trading
privileges for the United States. Now,
the European powers didn't pay it much
attention, but they didn't really reject
it either. So, hey, mark that one down
as a victory. and America held on to
some trading rights in that highly
desired Asian market. And then US
involvement only increased from there.
And then finally, the third effect of
the SpanishAmerican War was the need to
suppress a nationalist movement in the
Philippines. So even before US forces
were fighting Spain and Cuba, they also
launched an attack against Spanish
forces in the Philippines. And Filipino
forces fought alongside the Americans
during their invasion of Manila. And it
wasn't long before Spain surrendered.
And again, just like in Cuba, the
Filipinos had been fighting against the
Spanish long before the Americans showed
up and therefore made victory way
easier. But don't worry, America claimed
full responsibility for defeating Spain
as is our custom. But the Filipinos kind
of brushed that off because they were
free at long last with the help of the
United States, that bastion of liberty
and ardent defender of
self-determination on the world stage
for all nations. And
you see where this is going, right?
Yeah. As it turned out, the Philippines
was a critical territory that provided
access to those juicy Asian markets I
talked about a moment ago. Not to
mention, it was a fine place to set up
some naval bases. And so in 1898,
President McKinley decided the best move
was for the US to annex the Philippines.
And that was for two reasons. First, if
the US didn't step in and rule that
nation, then some other European
imperial nation would swoop in and do it
for them. Second, he didn't believe that
the Filipinos were capable of governing
themselves and therefore needed the
paternalistic hand of America to usher
them into the glories of American
civilization. And to put it mildly, the
Filipinos were not fans of this move.
Like, they had already been fighting for
their own independence against Spain.
And in the beginning, they welcomed
American troops because they believed it
would aid them in their fight for
freedom from imperial rule. And remember
that this move was also hotly debated by
Americans themselves. The most vocal
opposition coming from the
anti-imperialist league, to whom I
introduced you in the last video.
However, as soon as it became clear to
Filipinos that they were just trading
Spanish rule for American rule, the
Filipinos turned their fighting against
their new occupiers. So, a Filipino
nationalist named Alio Aguinonaldo led
the insurgency and the Filipinos made
use of the same guerilla tactics they
had used successfully against Spain. And
that severely annoyed the US because how
could these inferior people not
understand how backward they were and
how great American help would be for
them. And so US forces responded to the
uprising with brutal violence which
resulted in more than 200,000 deaths of
Filipino soldiers and civilians alike.
And finally in 1901, US troops captured
Auanaldo and the rebellion lost its main
source of energy. And at that the
Philippines came under direct control of
the United States with McKinley
appointing future President William
Howard Taft as the territorial governor.
And that, ladies and gentlemen, is how
the United States pulled its big boy
empire pants all the way up and came out
as a formidable power on the world
stage. All right, you can click here to
watch my other videos for unit 7, or you
can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain fold. And I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch you
on the flip-flop. Himler out.